<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Galactic Forensics Laboratory</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/</link><atom:link href="https://galactic-forensics.space/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Galactic Forensics Laboratory</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© (2022) · Galactic Forensics Laboratory · Brandeis University</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://galactic-forensics.space/images/logo_hueb41359ad733f2a4eb80221204fe0002_32021_300x300_fit_lanczos_2.png</url><title>Galactic Forensics Laboratory</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/</link></image><item><title>Stardust</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/project/stardust/</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 May 2020 15:34:09 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/project/stardust/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="formation-and-delivery">Formation and delivery&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Stardust grains condensed in the outflows of dying stars and subsequently drifted through the interstellar medium. By chance some of these grains were present in the solar nebula and got incorporated in the precursors of meteorites. Some of these meteorite parent bodies have never been altered throughout the history of the solar system. Thus, we can extract stardust grains from such primitive meteorites and analyze them in the laboratory. This allows us to directly probe the nucleosythetic fingerprint of the parent star from which a specific stardust grain formed. Since these grains formed prior to the solar system they are often referred to as presolar grains. The figure below shows a schematic on how we picture the history of these samples.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://galactic-forensics.space/img/projects/stardust/presolar_grains_origin_1600.png" alt="Origin of Stardust Grains">&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-age-of-stardust-grains">The age of stardust grains&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>During their time in the interstellar medium stardust grains were irradiated with galactic cosmic rays, i.e., high-energy protons and &lt;sup>4&lt;/sup>He nuclei. These high-energy particles induced spallogenic reactions (click
&lt;a href="https://galactic-forensics.space/project/cosnucs/">here&lt;/a> for more information) in the stardust grain. In a &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1904573117" target="_blank">recent study&lt;/a> these spallogenically produced nuclides were measured to determinme how long stardust grains traveled from their birthplace to the early solar system, i.e., to determine their cosmic ray exposure age. We found that most grains have condensed up to around 100 million years prior to solar system formation, however, there were also some very old grain among the analyzed ones which formed more than 3 billion years before solar system formation. These samples are thus more than 7 billion years old, which is more than half the age of the Milky Way. &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1904573117" target="_blank">Here&lt;/a> you can find a more detailed article on this study.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="encoded-stellar-information">Encoded stellar information&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Aside from slight modifications in the interstellar medium, stardust grains carry the nucleosynthetic fingerprint of their parent star. This means that these grains can be used as direct probes to better understand the formation of elements and isotopes in stars as well as the evolution of isotopes over the history of the galaxy. Since different grains originated in different stars, various stellar environments can be probed. For example, so called mainstream grains originated in low-mass stars, which are the main hosts of the slow neutron capture (&lt;em>s&lt;/em>-) process. These stars are responsible for producing around half of all elements heavier than iron. Mainstream grains can thus be directly used to probe this &lt;em>s&lt;/em>-process and gain valuable insights into the inner working of these nucleosynthesis sites.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Some isotopes however, e.g., &lt;sup>54&lt;/sup>Fe and &lt;sup>60&lt;/sup>Ni are not significantly affected in low-mass stars, meaning that what comes out of the star also went originally in. Such isotopes are thus proxies for the material from which the mainstream grain&amp;rsquo;s parent star formed and allow us to trace galactic chemical evolution. You can find more or on this topic
&lt;a href="https://galactic-forensics.space/project/gce">here&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="analyzing-stardust-grains">Analyzing stardust grains&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://galactic-forensics.space/img/projects/stardust/sic_grains_compilation.png" alt="SiC Stardust Grains">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The image above shows three different SiC grains that were extracted from the Murchison meteorite. The scalebars show that these grains are on the order of micrometers in size, and in fact, the grains shown here are large compared to many other SiC grains. As the name already says, SiC grains consist mainly of silicon and carbon. Elements of interest in order to study stellar nucleosynthesis and galactic chemical evolution are often only present in trace amounts. Special analytical techniques are thus required to get the most information out of these tiny samples. One of the most senstive techniques is resonance ionization mass spectrometry (RIMS). A description of its inner workings can be found
&lt;a href="https://galactic-forensics.space/project/rims">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Galactic Chemical Evolution</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/project/gce/</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 May 2020 15:34:09 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/project/gce/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="from-the-big-bang-to-today">From the Big Bang to today&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Galactic chemical evolution (GCE) is the field that studies how elements evolved in the universe. The big bang only produced hydrogen, helium, and a little bit of lithium. Aside from beryllium and boron, all other elements formed in stars in a process called nucleosynthesis. Depending on their initial masses stars undergo very different developments. A massive star can explode as a supernova at the end of its life while a low-mass star does not have enough energy stored up in order to explode so violently. Different elements and isotopes are associated with the production in different stellar environments. Galactic chemical evolution describes how this evolution of the elements took place since the beginning of the universe and is thus often described as galactic archeology. Below artistic impression (by Jenny Mottar, NASA) beautifully summarizes GCE in one image: from the big bang to complex molecules and the earth everything originates as stardust.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://galactic-forensics.space/img/projects/gce/gce_mottar.jpg" alt="GCE by Jenny Mottar">&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="metallicity">Metallicity&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The periodic chart of the elements as chemists use it can be hard to
remember, however, it is fairly easy for astronomers. In the
astronomical sense, the universe consists of hydrogen, helium, and metals (yes,
in the astronomical sense you breathe metals). The amount of metals in a star
with respect to hydrogen is called the metallicity. Mass fractions of hydrogen
to helium to metals are usually written in astronomy with the letters &lt;em>X&lt;/em>, &lt;em>Y&lt;/em>,
and &lt;em>Z&lt;/em>, respectively. The mass fractions of hydrogen, helium, and metals in the
sun for example are: &lt;em>X&lt;/em>&lt;sub>sun&lt;/sub> = 0.7381, &lt;em>Y&lt;/em>&lt;sub>sun&lt;/sub> = 0.2485, and
&lt;em>Z&lt;/em>&lt;sub>sun&lt;/sub> = 0.0134. Knowing this number for the sun, any star&amp;rsquo;s
metallicity can be expressed in terms of the solar metallicty. Metallicity can
however also be expressed as a chemical abundance ratio. Here, the abundance of
iron is often measured in a star and used as a proxy for the total metallicity.
This abundance ratio is typically written as:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$ [\rm{Fe}/\rm{H}] = \log_{10} \left( \frac{N_{\rm{Fe}}}{N_{\rm{H}}} \right)_{\rm{star}} - \log_{10} \left( \frac{N_{\rm{Fe}}}{N _{\rm{H}}} \right)_{\rm{sun}}$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Since the big bang did not produce metals a first order GCE model can assume that the metallicity of an object is correlated to its age, i.e., an older object started out with a lower metallicty. This is assumption is correct up to a certain degree, however, breaks down when looking at the details of GCE.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="observables">Observables&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="astronomical-observations">Astronomical observations&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Traditionally GCE is studied in detail by astronomical observations, specifically spectroscopy. This allows the determination of the elemental composition of stars and, in for certain elements, their isotopic composition. A variety of different stars can be observed, which allows us to study the distribution of elements within the galaxy. Furthermore, different stars have different ages. The elemental starting comopsition of a given star will be observable throughout most of its life, thus astronomical observations also allow us to look at GCE in time.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="stardust-grain-measurements">Stardust grain measurements&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Stardust grains also allow us to study GCE. While the elemental composition of these grains is primarily dominated by the chemistry of the condensing stellar outflow and is thus not representative of the parent star&amp;rsquo;s composition, stardust grains are excellent tracers for the isotopic comopsition of stars.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="silicon-isotopes-in-mainstream-grains-and-the-puzzling-conclusion">Silicon isotopes in mainstream grains and the puzzling conclusion&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The figure below shows the silicon isotopic composition of all mainstream SiC stardust grains from low-mass stars taken from the &lt;a href="https://presolar.physics.wustl.edu/presolar-grain-database/" target="_blank">presolar grain database&lt;/a>. Plotted are all measurement that have isotope ratio measurements with lower than 10‰ uncertainties.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://galactic-forensics.space/img/projects/gce/sic_si_isos.png" alt="SiC Stardust Silicon Isotopes">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The axes labels are in delta units and describe the deviation of the sample from a standard (here the solar average) in per thousands:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$ \delta ^{i}\rm{Si}_{28} = \left[\frac{\left(\frac{^{i}\rm{Si}}{^{28}\rm{Si}}\right) _{\rm{sample}}}{\left(\frac{^{i}\rm{Si}}{^{28}\rm{Si}}\right) _{\rm{standard}}} - 1\right] \times 1000 $$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The dashed line at the origin of the plot represents the solar isotopic composotion of silicon.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>From GCE calculations we expect that &lt;sup>28&lt;/sup>Si forms early on and that the isotopes &lt;sup>29&lt;/sup>Si and &lt;sup>30&lt;/sup>Si form later on from &lt;sup>28&lt;/sup>Si. Silicon-28 is thus also called a primary isotope, while &lt;sup>29,30&lt;/sup>Si are secondary isotopes. We know however that presolar grains are older than the solar system, thus the material from which their stars formed came together before the solar system formed. A low-mass star, such as each parent star of a grain shown in the figure above, does not effectively produce &lt;sup>29&lt;/sup>Si and only produces a little bit (a few tens of ‰) of &lt;sup>30&lt;/sup>Si. Silicon isotopes are thus excellent proxies to study GCE.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What is going on then in the figure above? A lot of the grains are clearly enriched in &lt;sup>29&lt;/sup>Si and &lt;sup>30&lt;/sup>Si compared to the solar system. In the age-metallicity correlated GCE picture these grains thus seem younger than the solar system. The silicon isotopic composition of presolar grains thus clearly requires that GCE takes place more heterogeneously.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="other-gce-proxies-tell-the-same-story">Other GCE proxies tell the same story&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>In a &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gca.2017.05.031" target="_blank">recent study&lt;/a> we tested if the same holds true for the isotopic composition of iron and nickel. The best isotopes to use as GCE proxies here are &lt;sup>54&lt;/sup>Fe and &lt;sup>60&lt;/sup>Ni. The figure below shows our results:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://galactic-forensics.space/img/projects/gce/gce_fe_ni_trappitsch18_380px.png" alt="Iron and Nickel Results in Presolar SiC Grains">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The dashed, purple line shows the GCE model by &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2966.2011.18621.x" target="_blank">Kobayashi et al. (2011)&lt;/a> in comparison with our measurements. This linear GCE model ends at solar composition and for older objects shows a decrease in &lt;sup>54&lt;/sup>Fe and an enhancement in &lt;sup>60&lt;/sup>Ni. Many of the measured stardust grains look more evolved than the solar system itself, which agrees with the silicion isotopic measurements and also requries GCE to take place heterogeneously.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Measurements of stardust grains along with astronomical observations yield important constraints for our understanding of GCE. Astronomical observations are often limited to determine the elemental abundance. Stardust grains on the other hand do not allow us to determine their exact parent star, however, enable an excellent understanding of the isotopic evolution of GCE. The two techniques are thus highly complementary for studying GCE.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Solar Nebula</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/project/slrs/</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 May 2020 15:34:09 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/project/slrs/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="the-composition-of-the-solar-nebula">The composition of the solar nebula&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The solar system formed around 4.5 billion years ago, which is around 9 billion years after the formation of the Milky Way itself. This means that the average solar composition that the solar nebula started with represents one datapoint in terms of galactic chemical evolution.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The solar composition can be measured excellently by observing the sun as well as by analyzing primitive meteorites. Except for volatile species, e.g., hydrogen and the noble gases, the composition of these two sample sets agree very well with each other. However, there are some anomalies that can be found in meteorites, which are very indicative of the exact circumstances under which the solar system formed.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="short-lived-radionuclides">Short-lived radionuclides&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Some of the anomalies that can be found in primitive objects from the solar system are enhancement in certain isotopes due to the in situ radioactive decay of short-lived radionuclides (SLRs). Calcium aluminum-rich refractory inclusions (CAIs), which are fluffy looking phases in primitive meteorites, are some of the very first material that condensed in the solar nebula and are the ideal samples to look for such anomalies.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="determining-the-abundance-of-slrs-in-the-solar-nebula">Determining the abundance of SLRs in the solar nebula&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>If for example the short-lived &lt;sup>60&lt;/sup>Fe was incorporated into a solid that condensed early on in the solar system we would be able to measure it today as an enhancement of &lt;sup>60&lt;/sup>Ni since the original &lt;sup>60&lt;/sup>Fe, which has a half-life of 2.6 Ma, would have all decayed to its stable daughter by now. The figure below shows how the presence of SLRs can be detected in a given sample.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://galactic-forensics.space/img/projects/slrs/fe60_isochron.png" alt="Schematic on Measuring an Isochron">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The figure on left shows the scenario at formation. Different minerals condense with different amounts of iron to nickel elemental compositions. The figure in the middle shows what happens with these different phases once they are solidified. The y-axis here always shows the &lt;sup>60&lt;/sup>Ni/&lt;sup>58&lt;/sup>Ni ratio. The more iron a phase condensed with the more &lt;sup>60&lt;/sup>Fe it will have incorporated as well. Thus, once all the &lt;sup>60&lt;/sup>Fe has decayed to &lt;sup>60&lt;/sup>Ni the phases will end up with different &lt;sup>60&lt;/sup>Ni/&lt;sup>58&lt;/sup>Ni ratios. The figure on the right shows the scenario today. By measuring different phases for their Fe/Ni elemental ratio (shwown on the x-axis) and their nickel isotopic composition (y-axis), the original value of the &lt;sup>60&lt;/sup>Fe/&lt;sup>56&lt;/sup>Fe at the time of condensation can be determined by fitting a line to these measurements. In above example this line will have the form:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$\frac{^{60}\rm{Ni}}{^{58}\rm{Ni}} = \left(\frac{^{60}\rm{Fe}}{^{56}\rm{Fe}}\right)_ 0 \times \frac{^{56}\rm{Fe}}{^{58}\rm{Ni}} + \left(\frac{^{60}\rm{Ni}}{^{58}\rm{Ni}}\right)_ 0$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Here, the isotope ratios with subscript 0 represent the initial composition of the isotope ratio when the phase condensed. The original &lt;sup>60&lt;/sup>Fe/&lt;sup>56&lt;/sup>Fe ratio is thus nothing else than the slope of the regression.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Assuming that an SLR was distributed homogeneously in the early solar system allows to also date phases relative to each other. For example, if one phase shows half the initial &lt;sup>60&lt;/sup>Fe/&lt;sup>56&lt;/sup>Fe than another phase we can say that the phase with less initial &lt;sup>60&lt;/sup>Fe condensed one &lt;sup>60&lt;/sup>Fe half life (2.6 Ma) after the first one.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="the-presence-of-sup26supal-and-its-effects">The presence of &lt;sup>26&lt;/sup>Al and its effects&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>One of the most prominent SLRs that has been shown to be present in the solar nebula is &lt;sup>26&lt;/sup>Al (half life 717 ka). Many studies have shown that &lt;sup>26&lt;/sup>Al was distributed homogeneously in the solar nebula and that its initial abundance when CAIs formed was $$^{26}\rm{Al}/^{27}\rm{Al} = 5\times10^{-5}$$. This has important implications because it allows us to date different phases in the early solar system relative to each other. Furhtermore, when &lt;sup>26&lt;/sup>Al decays to &lt;sup>26&lt;/sup>Mg it releases 4 MeV of energy. This is a significant amount and has been shown to be able to heat an asteroid parent body of a given size (and thus of a given &lt;sup>26&lt;/sup>Al content) significally. In fact, &lt;sup>26&lt;/sup>Al has been invoked as being a crucial heat source that started the differentiation of early planetesimals.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The presence of &lt;sup>26&lt;/sup>Al in the solar system raises the quesion on where it came from. Since its half-life is only 717 ka it had to be produced just prior to solar system formation. The key to decipher where it came from comes from studying other SLRs that were also present in the solar nebula.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="the-curious-case-of-sup60supfe-in-the-solar-nebula">The curious case of &lt;sup>60&lt;/sup>Fe in the solar nebula&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>One nuclide that can help us solve the question on where the &lt;sup>26&lt;/sup>Al in the early solar system came from is &lt;sup>60&lt;/sup>Fe. If &lt;sup>60&lt;/sup>Fe is also present in the solar nebula it was likely produced and injected along with &lt;sup>26&lt;/sup>Al. A large amount of &lt;sup>60&lt;/sup>Fe in the early solar nebula, by which we mean a value of $$^{60}\rm{Fe}/^{56}\rm{Fe} &amp;gt; 5\times10^{-7}$$ would make it likely that a supernova that exploded just before the solar system produced and injected the two nucldies. A low value of $$^{60}\rm{Fe}/^{56}\rm{Fe} \sim 10^{-8}$$ would however indicate that no such supernova took place and that the &lt;sup>60&lt;/sup>Fe does not need to be produced but is rather the galactic background value.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This discussion might seem very fabricated, however, for years and years the community has argued over the amount of &lt;sup>60&lt;/sup>Fe present in the solar nebula and the mentioned values are not just randomly picked. In situ studies of chondrules, objects that formed in the solar system about 2 Ma after CAIs, by secondary ion mass spectrometry (SIMS) showed high &lt;sup>60&lt;/sup>Fe values and thus pointed towards a supernova source. Bulk studies of many meteorites on the other hand consistently measured low &lt;sup>60&lt;/sup>Fe values. Until recently, the in situ measurements could not be tested with other techniques than SIMS.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In a &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.3847/2041-8213/aabba9" target="_blank">recent publication&lt;/a> we re-analyzed one chondrule with
&lt;a href="https://galactic-forensics.space/project/rims">resonance ionization mass spectrometry (RIMS)&lt;/a>. This sample has previously only been studied with SIMS. RIMS has the advantage over SIMS that all nickel isotopes can be measured without interferences. SIMS however can only anlyze &lt;sup>60&lt;/sup>Ni, &lt;sup>61&lt;/sup>Ni, and &lt;sup>62&lt;/sup>Ni. In order to determine the excess in &lt;sup>60&lt;/sup>Ni the measurements needs to be normalized to another isotope (see isochron figure above). Furthermore, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isotope_fractionation" target="_blank">mass dependent fractionation&lt;/a> also has to be corrected for, thus measuring a third isotope is required.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://galactic-forensics.space/img/projects/slrs/ni_isos_dap1.png" alt="Nickel isotopes in DAP1">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The above figure shows the new results obtained by RIMS (left, &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.3847/2041-8213/aabba9" target="_blank">Trappitsch et al., 2018&lt;/a>) versus a re-evaluation of the old results by SIMS (right, &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gca.2017.06.013" target="_blank">Telus et al., 2018&lt;/a>). To evaluate the SIMS measurements requires doing the described corrections with the low abundance isotope &lt;sup>61&lt;/sup>Ni. This results in extreme correlations of the uncertainties, which, if not adequately accounted for, can seem like excesses in &lt;sup>60&lt;/sup>Ni due to in situ decay of &lt;sup>60&lt;/sup>Fe. With RIMS however this problem does not exist. The figure on the left clearly shows that the errors are uncorrelated thanks to the ability to measure &lt;sup>58&lt;/sup>Ni.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Our recent re-evaluation has brought up issues with the data processing that has been done in the determination of the initial &lt;sup>60&lt;/sup>Fe abundance. It remains to be seen if this is the case for all samples, however, preliminary evaluations of other SIMS measurements show that the same problem occurs in the rest of the dataset. A supernova thus cannot have injected the &lt;sup>26&lt;/sup>Al and another source, e.g., &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.3847/1538-4357/aa992e" target="_blank">a Wolf-Rayet star&lt;/a>, is required to explain its high value in the solar nebula.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Resonance Ionization Mass Spectrometry</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/project/rims/</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 May 2020 15:34:09 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/project/rims/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="the-measurement-challenge">The measurement challenge&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Most of the large stardust grains are still only a few micrometers in size. Determining the trace element isotopic composition thus requries a very sensitive technique. In addition, the ideal technique should be able to determine between different isobars, i.e., be able to analyze isotopes of different elements that have the same mass, e.g., &lt;sup>58&lt;/sup>Fe and &lt;sup>58&lt;/sup>Ni, simultaneously.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="resonance-ionization-mass-spectrometry">Resonance ionization mass spectrometry&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Resonance ionization mass spectrometry (RIMS) is an ideal technique to analyze such particles. The following animation shows schematics on how RIMS works.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://galactic-forensics.space/img/projects/rims/rims_animation.gif" alt="RIMS Animation">&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Overview of a RIMS instrument. On the left is the target / sample that should be analyzed. Then ion optics will guide the ions in the time-of-flight mass spectrometer. In this part, ions are initially given the same energy and are then separated by mass over charge by the total flight time they take from the extractor to the detector. The blue box represents the resonance ionization lasers.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Material from a sample (target) is removed by either using an ion beam or a desorption laser.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>After removing sample material a mixture of mostly neutral atoms and secondary ions (usually less than 1%) will be present above the samples.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Since the secondary ions are generally noise in RIMS, they are ejected from the sampling area by applying a high voltage to the extraction optics. These secondary ions are given so much energy that they will fly into the back of the reflector and be neturalized there. They thus cannot reach the detector.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Above the sample a cloud of neutral atoms is left behind.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Resonance lasers ionize all isotopes of the elements of interest selectively creating photoions.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>By applying the correct voltages to the instrument the created photoions are extracted into the mass spectrometers and analyzed.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h3 id="resonance-ionization-with-tisapphire-lasers">Resonance ionization with Ti:Sapphire lasers&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The advantage of RIMS is the ionization of neutral atoms by tunable, resonant lasers. First of all this process is highly effective since almost all of the atoms that come off in the removal event are neutrals. Further, resonance ionization means that multiple lasers are tuned to stepwise and resonantly excite an atom until it is singly ionized. The figure below for example shows an example for the ionization of titanium.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://galactic-forensics.space/img/projects/rims/ti_ionization_scheme.png" alt="Ti Ionization Scheme">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This ionization scheme is taken from &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1039/C8JA00269J" target="_blank">Trappitsch et al. (2018)&lt;/a>. Shown are mutliple transitions for titanium, all of which are highly selective and effective for only this specific element, here titanium. Thus, other elements with potentially overlapping isobars are not ionized.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="mass-spectra">Mass spectra&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The figure below shows a mass spectrum recorded by RIMS for the quasi-simultaneous analysis of iron and nickel.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://galactic-forensics.space/img/projects/rims/feni_ms_sep.png" alt="RIMS Mass Spectrum for Iron and Nickel">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>While iron and nickel have an overlapping isobar at mass 58, the ionization of nickel was delayed by several hundred nanoseconds with respect to the ionization of nickel. In the time-of-flight mass analyzer this separation resulted in a separation of these two identical masses allowing the simultaneous detection of &lt;sup>58&lt;/sup>Fe and &lt;sup>58&lt;/sup>Ni. RIMS thus, compared to other techniques, allows us to analyze elements with inherent isobaric overlaps simultaneously for all isotopes.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="instruments">Instruments&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Currently only two RIMS instruments are being used for cosmochemistry worldwide, both of which I have worked on. These instruments are the &lt;a href="https://geosci.uchicago.edu/research/planetary-sciences-and-cosmochemistry/" target="_blank">CHILI (Chicago Instrument for Laser Ionization) instrument at the University of Chicago&lt;/a> and the &lt;a href="https://str.llnl.gov/january-2017/isselhardt" target="_blank">Livermore LION (Laser Ionization of Neutrals) instrument at Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://galactic-forensics.space/img/projects/rims/lion400px.jpg" alt="LION at LLNL">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The image above shows the LION instrument. The mass spectrometer can be seen on the right side, however, the reflectron (in this setup the top of the instrument) is outside the field of view. The center and left part shows the six tunable Ti:Sapphire lasers which allow the simultaneous ionization of various different elements.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Cosmic ray exposure ages</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/project/cosnucs/</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 May 2020 15:34:09 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/project/cosnucs/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="irradiation-of-bodies-in-space">Irradiation of bodies in space&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Objects in space are constantly irradiated with high-energy particles. Two sources of such particles exist in the solar system: solar cosmic rays (SCRs) originating from the sun and galactic cosmic rays (GCRs).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://galactic-forensics.space/img/projects/cosnucs/scr_gcr.png" alt="SCR and GCR Spectrum">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Above figure shows a comparison of the SCR (blue, solid line) and GCR (green, dashed line) spectrum. The SCR can only penetrate the upper few centimeters of any given material in space due to its low energies. On the other hand, GCRs can penetrate down to several meters below the surface of a given meteoroid. Since the outer layers of meteorites are generally lost, only the GCR flux matters when analyzing meteorites.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Note&lt;/em>: Scientists working on cosmogenic nuclides generally distinguish between meteoroids and meteorites. A meteoroid is an rock in space that broke off from its parent asteroid, is thus irradiated by SCR and GCR, and has not hit the Earth yet. A meteorite on the other hand is the rock that fell from the sky, i.e., the meteoroid after it fell down to earth, thus passed the atmosphere and lost most of its outer material by ablation. This ablation usually leads to a meteoroid loosing its SCR record such that only GCR effects can be measured in meteorites.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="spallation-reactions">Spallation reactions&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The irradiation of material in space with high-energy particles induced the production of spallogenic nuclides. The figure below shows a schematic on how spallogenic reactions take place on the example of a &lt;sup>28&lt;/sup>Si nucleus.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://galactic-forensics.space/img/projects/cosnucs/spallation_schematic.png" alt="Spallation Schematic">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In panel (1), a high energy proton strikes a target nucleus (here &lt;sup>28&lt;/sup>Si). This nucleus then breaks up
into various lighter nuclei (2). The excited nucleus left behind then decays, e.g., via γ or
neutron emission and a cosmogenic nuclide (here &lt;sup>21&lt;/sup>Ne) is left behind (3).
For a given high-energy particle &lt;em>k&lt;/em> (a proton for the example above) at a given energy &lt;em>E&lt;/em>, the production of a cosmogenic nuclide &lt;em>j&lt;/em> from a target element &lt;em>i&lt;/em> can be calculated as:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$P_{j,i,k} = \sigma_{j,i,k} J_k$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Here, &lt;em>J&lt;sub>k&lt;/sub>&lt;/em> describes the flux of the incident particle of a given energy. In a real scenario many target elements are present in a given meteoroid that can contribute to the production of nuclide &lt;em>j&lt;/em>. Furthermore, the GCR and SCR have a variety of different energies, see for example the figure showing the SCR and GCR spectrum above. The total production rate &lt;em>P&lt;sub>j&lt;/sub>&lt;/em> of nuclide &lt;em>j&lt;/em> in a meteoroid can then be calculated as:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$P_j = \sum_{i} c_i \frac{N_A}{A_i} \sum_k \int_0^{\infty} \sigma_{i,j,k} J_k(E)dE$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The first sum over &lt;em>i&lt;/em> considers the meteoroid&amp;rsquo;s composition. Here &lt;em>c&lt;sub>i&lt;/sub>&lt;/em> is the concentration of target nuclide &lt;em>i&lt;/em>, &lt;em>N&lt;sub>A&lt;/sub>&lt;/em> Avogadro&amp;rsquo;s constant, and &lt;em>A&lt;sub>i&lt;/sub>&lt;/em> the mean mass of nuclide &lt;em>i&lt;/em>. The production rate also depends on different target elements &lt;em>k&lt;/em>, to calculate the total production rate from all all projectiles we thus need to sum over &lt;em>k&lt;/em>. The nuclear cross sections are of course projectile &lt;em>k&lt;/em>, target nucleus &lt;em>i&lt;/em>, product &lt;em>j&lt;/em>, and energy &lt;em>E&lt;/em> dependent, while the flux of the high-energy particles depends on their energy &lt;em>E&lt;/em>. Integrating over all energies is thus required as well.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="cosmic-ray-exposure-ages">Cosmic ray exposure ages&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The irradiation of a meteorite space induces spallation reactions and leads to the production of so called cosmogenic nuclides. Cosmogenic nuclide production is generally a very minor contribution and thus can only be detected in low-abundance isotopes, e.g., noble gases. If for example the &lt;sup>21&lt;/sup>Ne composition in a given meteorite can be measured (&lt;em>m&lt;/em>) and the production rate &lt;em>P&lt;sub>j&lt;/sub>&lt;/em> can be calculated, the time the object was irradiated in space can be determined as:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$t = \frac{m}{P_j}$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The time &lt;em>t&lt;/em> is generally referred to as the cosmic ray exposure age of the sample. This technique has for example been used in order to determine the age of stardust grains in a &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1904573117" target="_blank">recent study&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Code Development</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/project/code/</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 May 2020 15:34:09 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/project/code/</guid><description>&lt;p>Research is fun when it consists of new and unique tasks. For repetitive ones on the other hand, computers are uniquely suited. Furthermore, in order to run
&lt;a href="https://galactic-forensics.space/project/rims/">RIMS instruments&lt;/a> control software is required. We have worked and are currently engaged in multiple code development projects. You can find many of these projects on the &lt;a href="https://github.com/galactic-forensics" target="_blank">lab&amp;rsquo;s GitHub page&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://github.com/trappitsch" target="_blank">Reto&amp;rsquo;s GitHub page&lt;/a>, or the &lt;a href="https://github.com/RIMS-Code" target="_blank">RIMS-Code GitHub page&lt;/a>. Below we outline some notable projects.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Note&lt;/em>: We are strong supporters of free and open source software (&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free_and_open-source_software" target="_blank">FOSS&lt;/a>). Scientific research is generally paid for by the taxpayer. The outcome should thus be freely available for everyone. We strive to publish all software under open source licenses and only use open source software in our daily life.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.python.org" target="_blank">&lt;img src="https://galactic-forensics.space/img/projects/code/python_logo.png" alt="Python Logo">&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As you will notice, a dominating programming language in our lab is Python. This becomes especially clear when you look at the GitHub pages given above. If you are interested in any of our specific code or you have questions, please feel free to
&lt;a href="https://galactic-forensics.space/contact/">contact us&lt;/a>! Also, contributions to our codes are always welcomed. Please have a look at the developer guides (when available). Feel free to create pull requests for documentation enhancement, small bug fixes, etc. We are looking forward to your ideas and issues.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="iniabu">iniabu&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;code>iniabu&lt;/code> is a package for python that you can use
to easily calculate the inital abundances of the solar system
and return ratios as δ-values or in bracket notation.
By default the initial abundances from
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-540-88055-4_34" target="_blank">Lodders et al. (2009)&lt;/a>
are used.
You can install this module by simply calling:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-console">pip install iniabu
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>The full documentation of &lt;code>iniabu&lt;/code> can be found
&lt;a href="https://iniabu.rtfd.io" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here&lt;/a>.
Full examples in the form of jupyter notebooks
can be found
&lt;a href="https://github.com/galactic-forensics/iniabu/tree/master/docs/jupyter_examples" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here&lt;/a>.
This package is completely rewritten from its first version.
It is also fully open source,
the code base is available on
&lt;a href="https://github.com/galactic-forensics/iniabu" target="_blank" rel="noopener">our GitHub page&lt;/a>.
On that page are also instructions on how to install the latest development version,
how to install from source,
and how to contribute.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>On the GitHub page
there is also a discussion section
where users are encouraged to share examples
and ask questions on usage.
Furthermore,
you can raise an issue
if you find a bug in the software,
would like some specific feature included,
or need help.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="instrumentkit">InstrumentKit&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The freely available &lt;a href="https://github.com/Galvant/InstrumentKit" target="_blank">InstrumentKit&lt;/a>
has been used to interact with hardware for the LION instrument
at Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory.
Several classes have been contributed by us
to this excellent compilation of tools.
This allows you and anybody else in the world to utilize more tools,
might motivate you to continue down the Python path,
and contribute your own instruments one day.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="mahon-fitting">Mahon Fitting&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In order to fit a linear regression to measurements with uncertainties in both axes, the routine by &lt;a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/00206819709465336" target="_blank">Mahon (1996)&lt;/a>, also known as the “New York” regression, should be used. Along with the &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.3847/2041-8213/aabba9" target="_blank">Trappitsch et al. (2018)&lt;/a> publication we published a tool to easily apply the Mahon fitting routine to any dataset. The tool, including a detailed README file, can be found on &lt;a href="https://github.com/LLNL/MahonFitting" target="_blank">the respective GitHub site&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="resonance-ionization-scheme-drawer">Resonance Ionization Scheme Drawer&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Would you like to make resonance ionization schemes like the one we show
&lt;a href="https://galactic-forensics.space/project/rims/">here&lt;/a> for titanium? Check out our &lt;a href="https://github.com/RIMS-Code/RIMSSchemeDrawer" target="_blank">&lt;code>RIMS Scheme Drawer&lt;/code>&lt;/a> software. This GUI allows you to draw your own resonance ionization schemes with just a few clicks and results in publishable figures.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://github.com/RIMS-Code/RIMSSchemeDrawer" target="_blank">&lt;img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/RIMS-Code/RIMSSchemeDrawer/master/examples/screenshot_titanium.png" alt="RIMSSchemeDrawer">&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="coordinate-transformation">Coordinate Transformation&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>If you work with samples in various instruments, our coordinate transfer program might be of interest to you. Assuming you have coordinates for your particles, our program allows you easily transfer these coordinates from one system into the other. You can use fiducial marks or simply find some of your sample positions again and start from there.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://github.com/trappitsch/CoordinateTransformation" target="_blank">&lt;img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/trappitsch/CoordinateTransformation/master/docs/screenshot-full.png" alt="Coordinate Transformation">&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Enjoy, and if you want, the source code is there for you as well!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Resources for Programming</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/resources/mind-bytes/resources_programming/</link><pubDate>Tue, 25 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/resources/mind-bytes/resources_programming/</guid><description>&lt;p>Sooner or later, most scientist have to automate certain tasks.
It is generally advisable to leave such repetitive things that can be
automated to the computer. Here we have a look at tools that might help with
this task.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>First things first: this is by no means going to be a comprehensive article,
but will rather be my own, fairly biased view, which heavily focuses on
&lt;a href="https://www.python.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&lt;code>python&lt;/code>&lt;/a> and
&lt;a href="https://git-scm.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&lt;code>git&lt;/code>&lt;/a>.
It hopefully starts simple, and then gets more advanced fast.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="python">Python&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Python is a scripted computer language that allows you to do many scientific
tasks, e.g., data evaluation, automatically. It is a fairly simple language to
learn, and you can get going fast, however, be open to learn more advanced
techniques later on. This means: Never stop learning! Python has many advanced
capabilities that can make your life easier and faster.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="learning-python">Learning Python&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>
&lt;a href="https://software-carpentry.org/lessons/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Software Carpentry&lt;/a> has two great
lessons on &lt;code>python&lt;/code>, which are especially suited for beginners. These lessons
should give you an introduction and overview of the language, but also teach
you how to plot figures using &lt;code>matplotlib&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A great book to introduce you python was written by Allen Downy and can
be found
&lt;a href="https://greenteapress.com/wp/think-python-2e/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here&lt;/a>. It is available
for free. The book gives an in-depth introduction into &lt;code>python&lt;/code>, but also into
the basics behind the language. Such knowledge is always helpful later on,
since it gives you a deeper understanding of certain behavior.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="working-with-python">Working with Python&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The official &lt;code>python&lt;/code> distribution is distributed from
&lt;a href="https://www.python.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener">python.org&lt;/a>.
If you install this distribution, you can add further packages using
&lt;a href="https://pip.pypa.io/en/stable/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&lt;code>pip&lt;/code>&lt;/a>.
However, this is not always the most straight forward way to work with &lt;code>python&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="virtual-environments">Virtual environments&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Virtual environments should be considered for all your projects. Depending
on what &lt;code>python&lt;/code> environment you are using, these environments will be
created different. It is worth looking into it.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="anaconda">Anaconda&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>For data processing and scientific python, check out
&lt;a href="https://www.anaconda.com/products/individual" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Anaconda&lt;/a>. This gives you a
&lt;code>conda&lt;/code> environment for &lt;code>python&lt;/code>. Furthermore, Anaconda comes with many
packages pre-installed and has a graphical manager to handle your distribution.
This can be advantageous, depending on what you need.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="pyenv">&lt;code>pyenv&lt;/code>&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>If you need to handle multiple different python versions and want
to easily manage virtual environments, check out
&lt;a href="https://github.com/pyenv/pyenv" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&lt;code>pyenv&lt;/code>&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="jupyter">Jupyter&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Finally, Jupyter Notebooks give a straight forward interface
to &lt;code>python&lt;/code> that allow you to play and develop code in a browser, as well as
to document it in
&lt;a href="https://www.markdownguide.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Markdown&lt;/a>.
Googles flavor of Jupyter is called
&lt;a href="https://colab.research.google.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Google Collab&lt;/a> and run on the web.
JetBrains, the creator of PyCharm, also has an online Jupyter Notebook
Server with is especially great for developing at the same time. It is
called
&lt;a href="https://datalore.jetbrains.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Datalore&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For Astrophysics, especially if you are interested in
&lt;a href="https://nugrid.github.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">NuGrid&lt;/a> data, check out the
&lt;a href="https://astrohub.uvic.ca/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Astrohub&lt;/a>. You can log into the public outreach
server with your GitHub account and then use a JupyterLab environment to run
your astrophysics models.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="editors">Editors&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Many good python editors exist. Personally, I prefer
&lt;a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/pycharm/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">PyCharm&lt;/a>, however, many other options.
PyCharm is a fully integrated developer environment (IDE) and comes with many
more tools than you need in the beginning, it can therefore be overwhelming at
first.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Other notable editors are
&lt;a href="https://www.spyder-ide.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Spyder&lt;/a>, which is a full
IDE that comes pre-installed with Anaconda. Also notable is
&lt;a href="https://www.sublimetext.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sublime Text&lt;/a>, which works in my workflow
especially well for scripting.
&lt;a href="https://www.tabnine.com/blog/python-on-sublime-text/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Here&lt;/a>
is a great article on how to set up Sublime Text for python.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="guis">GUIs&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>If you are interested in creating graphical user interfaces for your programs,
it is worth looking into GUIs. Two potential GUI creation packages that you
might want to consider using are
&lt;a href="https://www.riverbankcomputing.com/software/pyqt/intro/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&lt;code>PyQt&lt;/code>&lt;/a> or
&lt;a href="https://wiki.qt.io/PySide2" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&lt;code>PySide&lt;/code>&lt;/a>.
Great tutorials on Qt can be found
&lt;a href="https://www.pythonguis.com/pyqt5-tutorial/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you want to package your GUIs with installers,
check out
&lt;a href="https://build-system.fman.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&lt;code>fbs&lt;/code>&lt;/a>. Note that the open / free
version only supports &lt;code>python-3.6&lt;/code> and is restricted to &lt;code>PyQt5&lt;/code>. If you want
to dabble with the pro version, let me know.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="advanced-python">Advanced Python&lt;/h3>
&lt;h4 id="auto-formatting">Auto-formatting&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Formatting &lt;code>python&lt;/code> code should adhere - for readability - to certain rules.
These are often also referred as linting requirements. While it is tedious to
format code by hand, automatic formatters are very helpful. I generally use
&lt;a href="https://github.com/psf/black" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&lt;code>black&lt;/code>&lt;/a> to format my &lt;code>python&lt;/code> code.
The beauty of this is that it there are not many possibilities to format your
code, therefore, most of the decisions are already made, and it always looks
awesome. Various plugins exist that can be used in editors and IDEs.
&lt;a href="https://www.duckduckgo.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Search engines&lt;/a> are useful to find them.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="test-your-code">Test your code!&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Testing of code is crucial, since you generally want to make sure that your
scripts, functions, classes, etc., do what you want them to do.
An amazing package to test your python code is
&lt;a href="https://docs.pytest.org/en/6.2.x/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&lt;code>pytest&lt;/code>&lt;/a>. If you are interested in
learning testing with python, check out Brian Okken&amp;rsquo;s book
&lt;a href="https://pythontest.com/pytest-book/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="git">Git&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>When working with code, version control should be an integral part of your
workflow. One way of controlling versions is with &lt;code>git&lt;/code>.
The Galactic Forensics Laboratory has its &lt;code>git&lt;/code> repositories hosted
&lt;a href="https://github.com/galactic-forensics" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here on GitHub&lt;/a>. Lab members get
access to all repositories of the lab.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="learning-git">Learning &lt;code>git&lt;/code>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The best way to learn &lt;code>git&lt;/code> and / or to review your skill is by going through
&lt;a href="https://swcarpentry.github.io/git-novice/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">this course on Software Carpentry&lt;/a>.
The next step is then to use &lt;code>git&lt;/code> and, if you want to keep your repos online,
a service such as
&lt;a href="https://github.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">GitHub&lt;/a>. You can also browse the &lt;code>git&lt;/code>
book, which is available for free
&lt;a href="https://git-scm.com/book/en/v2" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The beauty of &lt;code>git&lt;/code> is that you can most of the time go back in time if you
made a mistake. So don&amp;rsquo;t worry if something happens! A good resource for
these weird cases is
&lt;a href="https://dangitgit.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Dangit Git&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="good-practices">Good practices&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>If you want to contribute code to a repository of which you are not a
maintainer, you should fork the repository to your own GitHub account.
Then create a branch with an appropriate name for the feature you want to
contribute. Add your changes, push your branch to your fork, and then create
a pull request where you describe what you have changed and why. Keep it short,
but descriptive.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Most projects, e.g., the
&lt;a href="https://github.com/galactic-forensics/iniabu" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&lt;code>iniabu&lt;/code>&lt;/a>
project have a developers guide that gives you additional information on
how to contribute. For &lt;code>iniabu&lt;/code>, you can find the guide, e.g.,
&lt;a href="https://iniabu.readthedocs.io/en/latest/dev/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here in the docs&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="advanced-git-and-github">Advanced &lt;code>git&lt;/code> and GitHub&lt;/h3>
&lt;h4 id="pre-commit">&lt;code>pre-commit&lt;/code>&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>If you are using &lt;code>git&lt;/code> regularly, especially on public projects, &lt;code>pre-commit&lt;/code>
can help you to automate tasks. You can install so-called &lt;code>hooks&lt;/code> that help
you perform various tasks, e.g., formatting, etc. Check out the
&lt;a href="https://pre-commit.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&lt;code>pre-commit&lt;/code> website&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="github-actions">GitHub Actions&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>For automatic testing on GitHub, consider using
&lt;a href="https://github.com/features/actions" target="_blank" rel="noopener">GitHub Actions&lt;/a>. These actions can
especially help when using continuous integration (CI).&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="some-more-advanced-resources">Some more advanced resources&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="code-coverage">Code coverage&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>When testing your python code, it is useful to know how many lines of your
code are actually tested by your test suite. To automate this process,
you can, e.g., use GitHub hooks for
&lt;a href="https://coveralls.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&lt;code>coveralls&lt;/code>&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="documentation">Documentation&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Last, but surely not least, you will likely make extensive use of great
documentations that you can find online. For &lt;code>python&lt;/code> code, automatic
documentation using your doc strings can be really helpful. One tool to do so
is
&lt;a href="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/en/master/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&lt;code>sphinx&lt;/code>&lt;/a>.
This is especially powerful in combination with
&lt;a href="https://readthedocs.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ReadTheDocs&lt;/a>, which can also be implemented with
a GitHub hook.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="hypermodern-python">Hypermodern Python&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Finally, if you want to code in &lt;code>python&lt;/code> using many bells and whistles,
check out the blog articles on hypermodern python by Claudio Jolowicz.
The series can be found
&lt;a href="https://cjolowicz.github.io/posts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here&lt;/a>, the
first article
&lt;a href="https://cjolowicz.github.io/posts/hypermodern-python-01-setup/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Introduction to Building Electronics Projects with Arduino</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/resources/courses/arduino_electronics/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/resources/courses/arduino_electronics/</guid><description>&lt;p>Scientific experiments often require that
scientists build their own setup.
Inexpensive microelectronics, such as
&lt;a href="https://www.arduino.cc" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Arduino&lt;/a>,
can furthermore help to automate certain repetitive tasks.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this workshop,
students with a basic understanding of electrical circuits
learn how to develop a scientific setup using Arduino.
They are introduced to various components step-by-step
until the final project,
an Arduino controlled sample cooling stage,
is fully implemented and working.
The notes for the workshop are intended for students
to go through them by themselves
and do the exercises.
In my opinion,
a topic such as this one can only be learned
by exercises, tinkering, and playing with the components.
Therefore, the workshop notes encourage students to do exactly that.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>All documents, code solutions, answers to questions, 3d designs, wiring diagrams,
etc. of this course,
including the LaTeX source files are available on
&lt;a href="https://github.com/galactic-forensics/workshop_arduino_electronics" target="_blank" rel="noopener">GitHub&lt;/a>.
All original files are published under the
&lt;a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License&lt;/a>.
A direct link to the lecture note PDF file is also given
on top of this page.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Curious Case of $^{60}$Fe in the Early Solar System</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/resources/presentations/2021-09-22-nic/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/resources/presentations/2021-09-22-nic/</guid><description>&lt;p>This invited talk reviews the discrepancies between in situ and bulk measurements
of the initial &lt;sup>60&lt;/sup>Fe abundance in the early Solar System. The
abundance of this short-lived radionuclide is important to constrain precisely
since it informs the source that contributed the &lt;sup>26&lt;/sup>Al that was present
in the solar nebula. The presentation discusses the new re-evaluation of the
in-situ secondary ion mass spectrometry (SIMS) measurements and discusses
the implications of this re-evaluation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The talk was presented at the 16&lt;sup>th&lt;/sup> Symposium on Nuclei in the Cosmos.
A link to the meeting website can be found
&lt;a href="https://indico.juna.ac.cn/event/1/" target="_blank">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Simultaneous Isotopic Analysis of U, Pu, and Am in Spent Nuclear Fuel by Resonance Ionization Mass Spectrometry</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/savina-21-analchem/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/savina-21-analchem/</guid><description/></item><item><title>On the Origin of Elements in the Milky Way</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/resources/courses/origin_elements/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/resources/courses/origin_elements/</guid><description>&lt;p>The Big Bang only formed hydrogen and helium. All other elements,
e.g., the ones we are made of,
were subsequently formed in stars. This course discusses how these elements
formed and how we can directly measure and probe nucleosynthesis and galactic
chemical evolution.
The course starts with the solar composition, i.e.,
the composition of the Solar System that we are ultimately trying to explain.
It then goes back to the Big Bang to start with the first nucleosynthesis events.
From here on, the course loops through various stellar nucleosynthesis events
and discusses observations and measurements along the way that help us
to understand how the elements we are all made of formed in the first place.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This course was first held at Brandeis University in Spring 2021
and is geared as an elective course towards advanced undergraduates and
early graduate students. The course is design as a mixture between
lectures and reading / discussion of original scientific manuscripts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>All documents, homework sets, etc. of this course,
including the LaTeX source files are available on
&lt;a href="https://github.com/galactic-forensics/lecture_origin_elements" target="_blank" rel="noopener">GitHub&lt;/a>.
All original files are published under the
&lt;a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License&lt;/a>.
A direct link to the lecture note PDF file is also given
on top of this page.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Resonance Ionization Mass Spectrometry (RIMS): Fundamentals and Applications Including Secondary Neutral Mass Spectrometry</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/savina-21-book/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/savina-21-book/</guid><description/></item><item><title>New Opportunities with Stardust</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/resources/presentations/2020-12-02-jina-horizons/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/resources/presentations/2020-12-02-jina-horizons/</guid><description>&lt;p>This brief presentation reviews some recent highlights of stardust research
and how it can be used to better understand astrophysical processes such as
the slow neutron capture process and the formation of proton- and neutron-rich
nuclides. Finally, the presentation discusses future opportunities with stardust
and how these measurements could help to further our knowledge of
galactic chemical evolution.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The talk was presented at the virtual 2020 JINA Horizons Meeting.
A link to the meeting website can be found
&lt;a href="https://indico.frib.msu.edu/event/39/" target="_blank">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>iniabu: Getting Solar System Abundances in Python</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/resources/presentations/2020-10-27-nugrid/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/resources/presentations/2020-10-27-nugrid/</guid><description>&lt;p>A brief presentation to discuss the current status of the
&lt;code>iniabu&lt;/code> package available on
&lt;a href="https://github.com/galactic-forensics/iniabu" target="_blank">GitHub&lt;/a>.
Some short demonstrations are given.
A more complete usage guide can be found
&lt;a href="https://iniabu.readthedocs.io" target="_blank">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Fall, Recovery, Classification and Initial Characterization of the Hamburg, Michigan H4 Chondrite</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/heck-20-hamburg/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/heck-20-hamburg/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Cosmic ray effects on the isotope composition of hydrogen and noble gases in lunar samples: Insights from Apollo 12018</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/fueri-20/</link><pubDate>Mon, 31 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/fueri-20/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Origin of large meteoritic SiC stardust grains in metal-rich AGB stars</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/lugaro-20/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/lugaro-20/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Links</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/resources/links/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/resources/links/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is a collection of links that we use regularly or want to keep in mind. Hopefully, you find something useful here as well in this quite random assortment. Also: This page will be updated when we come across something new and nice. Also feel free to propose some ideas on what you think is great.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="cosmochemistry-news">Cosmochemistry News&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://apod.nasa.gov/apod/astropix.html" target="_blank">Astronomy Picture of the Day&lt;/a>: Classics are always in style!&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/" target="_blank">ArXiV&lt;/a>: Physics / Astrophysics preprint server.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://cosmochemistry-papers.com/" target="_blank">Cosmochemistry papers&lt;/a>: Great resource that publishes the lates publications related to cosmochemistry&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="databases">Databases&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="http://web2.lac.u-psud.fr/lac/Database/Contents.html" target="_blank">Actinide atomic spectra&lt;/a>: Special atomic energy and spectra database for actinides. Has much more information than NIST database for these elements.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.oecd-nea.org/janis/" target="_blank">JANIS&lt;/a>: OECD-NEA nuclear data information system. Online tool and java based software available.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.nist.gov/pml/atomic-spectra-database" target="_blank">NIST Atomic spectra database&lt;/a>: Database for looking up atomic energies and spectra.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="http://riliselements.web.cern.ch/riliselements/index.php?location=all&amp;lasuse=all&amp;special=none" target="_blank">RILIS&lt;/a>: Database with RIMS spectra, maintained by CERN.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3>Instrumentation / Hardware&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://github.com/Galvant/InstrumentKit" target="_blank">Instrument Kit&lt;/a>: Driver / communication package for communication between Python and Hardware.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3>Software&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://github.com/kmiernik/Chart-of-nuclides-drawer" target="_blank">Chart of the nuclide drawer&lt;/a>: Python script to plot the whole chart of the nuclides using the nuclear data wallet numbers and prints it as an svg. Color scheme based on Karlsruher Nuklidkart but can be customized.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://inkscape.org/en/" target="_blank">Inkscape&lt;/a>: A classic at this point I assume, Inkscape is amazing when handling vector graphics and importing / exporting for proper figure handling. And best of all, fully open source.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://veusz.github.io/" target="_blank">Veusz&lt;/a>: Finally an open source tool to replace expensive plotting programs. Absolutely fantastic program!&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="http://yt-project.org/" target="_blank">yt-project&lt;/a>: If you need python and don&amp;rsquo;t want to install from scratch, look no further. YT is the solution to any of your problems.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Lifetimes of interstellar dust from cosmic-ray exposure ages of presolar silicon carbide</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/heck-20-cre/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/heck-20-cre/</guid><description/></item><item><title>NuGrid stellar data set - III. Updated low-mass AGB models and s-process nucleosynthesis with metallicities Z=0.01, Z=0.02 and Z=0.03</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/battino-19-nugrid-3/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/battino-19-nugrid-3/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Presolar Silicon Carbide Grains of Types Y and Z: Their Molybdenum Isotopic Compositions and Stellar Origins</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/liu-19-mo-yz/</link><pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/liu-19-mo-yz/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Molybdenum Isotopes in Presolar Silicon Carbide Grains: Details of s-process Nucleosynthesis in Parent Stars and Implications for r- and p-processes</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/stephan-19/</link><pubDate>Fri, 31 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/stephan-19/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Core-Collapse Supernovae and Multi-Messenger Astronomy</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/fryer-19/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/fryer-19/</guid><description/></item><item><title>MMA SAG: Thermonuclear Supernovae</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/zingale-19/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/zingale-19/</guid><description/></item><item><title>$^{60}$Fe in core-collapse supernovae and prospects for X-ray and gamma-ray detection in supernova remnants</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/jones-19/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/jones-19/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Contact</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/contact/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/contact/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Group Members</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/menu-group-members/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/menu-group-members/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Electronic excitation of uranium atoms sputtered from uranium metal and oxides</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/savina-18-spec/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/savina-18-spec/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Iron and nickel isotope compositions of presolar silicon carbide grains from supernovae</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/kodolanyi-18/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/kodolanyi-18/</guid><description/></item><item><title>New Constraints on the Major Neutron Source in Low-mass AGB Stars</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/liu-18-b/</link><pubDate>Thu, 27 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/liu-18-b/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Resonance ionization of titanium: high useful yield and new autoionizing states</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/trappitsch-18-jaas/</link><pubDate>Thu, 13 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/trappitsch-18-jaas/</guid><description/></item><item><title>New Resonance Ionization Mass Spectrometry Scheme for Improved Uranium Analysis</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/savina-18-analchem/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/savina-18-analchem/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Potassic, high-silica Hadean crust</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/boehnke-18-pnas/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/boehnke-18-pnas/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Chronology of Martian breccia NWA 7034 and implications for formation of the Martian crustal dichotomy</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/cassata-18/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/cassata-18/</guid><description/></item><item><title>New Constraints for the Abundance of $^{60}$Fe in the Early Solar System</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/trappitsch-18-apjl/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/trappitsch-18-apjl/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Common Occurrence of Explosive Hydrogen Burning in Type II Supernovae</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/liu-18-apj/</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/liu-18-apj/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Effects of Plume Hydrodynamics and Oxidation on the Composition of a Condensing Laser-Induced Plasma</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/weisz-18/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/weisz-18/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Simultaneous iron and nickel isotopic analyses of presolar silicon carbide grains</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/trappitsch-18-gca/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/trappitsch-18-gca/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Strontium and barium isotopes in presolar silicon carbide grains measured with CHILI—two types of X grains</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/stephan-18/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/stephan-18/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The neutron capture process in the He shell in core-collapse supernovae: Presolar silicon carbide grains as a diagnostic tool for nuclear astrophysics</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/pignatari-18/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/pignatari-18/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The production rate of cosmogenic deuterium at the Moon's surface</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/fueri-17/</link><pubDate>Mon, 17 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/fueri-17/</guid><description/></item><item><title>J-type Carbon Stars: A Dominant Source of $^{14}$N-rich Presolar SiC Grains of Type AB</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/liu-17/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/liu-17/</guid><description/></item><item><title>High Useful Yield and Isotopic Analysis of Uranium by Resonance Ionization Mass Spectrometry</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/savina-17/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/savina-17/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Neon produced by solar cosmic rays in ordinary chondrites</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/roth-17/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/roth-17/</guid><description/></item><item><title>CHILI – the Chicago Instrument for Laser Ionization – a new tool for isotope measurements in cosmochemistry</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/stephan-16/</link><pubDate>Sat, 20 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/stephan-16/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Diffusion of helium in SiC and implications for retention of cosmogenic He</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/cherniak-16/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/cherniak-16/</guid><description/></item><item><title>NuGrid stellar data set. I. Stellar yields from H to Bi for stars with metallicities Z= 0.02 and Z= 0.01</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/pignatari-16/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/pignatari-16/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Application of a theory and simulation-based convective boundary mixing model for AGB star evolution and nucleosynthesis</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/battino-16/</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/battino-16/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Production and recoil loss of cosmogenic nuclides in presolar grains</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/trappitsch-16-cosnucpsg/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/trappitsch-16-cosnucpsg/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Noble gases in 18 Martian meteorites and angrite Northwest Africa 7812—Exposure ages, trapped gases, and a re‐evaluation of the evidence for solar cosmic ray‐produced neon in shergottites and other achondrites</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/wieler-16/</link><pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/wieler-16/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Carbon-rich presolar grains from massive stars: Subsolar $^{12}$C/$^{13}$C and $^{14}$N/$^{15}$N ratios and the mystery of $^{15}$N</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/pignatari-15/</link><pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/pignatari-15/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Solar cosmic-ray interaction with protoplanetary disks: Production of short-lived radionuclides and amorphization of crystalline material</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/trappitsch-15/</link><pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/trappitsch-15/</guid><description/></item><item><title>MESA and NuGrid simulations of classical novae: CO and ONe nova nucleosynthesis</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/denissenkov-2014-nova/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/denissenkov-2014-nova/</guid><description/></item><item><title>He and Ne in individual chromite grains from the regolith breccia Ghubara (L5): Exploring the history of the L chondrite parent body regolith</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/meier-2014/</link><pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/meier-2014/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Silicon carbide grains of type C provide evidence for the production of the unstable isotope $^{32}$Si in supernovae</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/pignatari-2013-silicon/</link><pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/pignatari-2013-silicon/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Cosmogenic production rates and recoil loss effects in micrometeorites and interplanetary dust particles</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/trappitsch-2013-cosmogenic/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/publication/trappitsch-2013-cosmogenic/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Downloads</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/resources/downloads/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/resources/downloads/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="fe-ni-presolar-grain-measurements">Fe, Ni presolar grain measurements&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Data from Trappitsch et al. (2018)&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;a href="https://galactic-forensics.space/files/downloads/trappitsch_et_al_2018/Trappitsch&amp;#43;2018_datatable_corrected_d64Ni.xlsb">Here&lt;/a>. you can find the data from &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gca.2017.05.031" target="_blank">Trappitsch et al. (2018)&lt;/a> in a machine readable format. Note that the δ&lt;sup>64&lt;/sup>Ni measurements are slightly corrected compared to the paper. While the conclusions from Trappitsch et al. (2018) do not change, we found a slight normalization error, which is corrected in the table provided
&lt;a href="https://galactic-forensics.space/files/downloads/trappitsch_et_al_2018/Trappitsch&amp;#43;2018_datatable_corrected_d64Ni.xlsb">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="cosmogenic--nuclides-in-micrometeorites-and-ipds-induced">Cosmogenic nuclides in micrometeorites and IPDs induced&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Supplement to Trappitsch &amp;amp; Leya (2013)&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/maps.12051" target="_blank">Trappitsch and Leya (2013)&lt;/a> we presented new cosmogenic production rates in micrometeorites and interplanetary dust particles. Here we provide the Excel tables from the paper for download.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://galactic-forensics.space/files/downloads/trappitsch_leya_2013/SCR_Cosmogenic_Nuclides_in_IDPs.xls">SCR induced cosmogenic nuclides&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://galactic-forensics.space/files/downloads/trappitsch_leya_2013/GCR_Cosmogenic_Nuclides_in_IDPs.xls">GCR induced cosmogenic nuclides&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Projects</title><link>https://galactic-forensics.space/menu-projects/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://galactic-forensics.space/menu-projects/</guid><description/></item></channel></rss>